Guide to the Erasmus Hall Records 1325–1989 (bulk circa 1775–1975) MS 201
New-York Historical Society
- "Archives of Erasmus Hall High School"
  - Strong, Robert Grier (Erasmus Hall Academy principal, 1879–1892)
    - [Letter submitting Annual Report for 1888–89], 1889 February 8 (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Academy Trustees' Correspondence)
      Holograph letter, written and signed by Strong, dated Feb. 8, 1889, submitting Annual Report for 1888–89 to Trustees of Academy. 7 pg. letter.
    - [Letter regarding a list of the Academy's scholars since its founding], 1889 February 9 (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Academy Trustees' Correspondence)
      Holograph letter, signed, dated Feb. 9, 1889, with reference to compiling a list of all of the Academy's students since its founding. "I have succeeded in securing six hundred and thirty-eight names (638) between the years of 1815–1846."
  - Strong, Thomas M.
    - [Photograph of portrait], undated (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder Rev. Thomas M. Strong)
      Small, mounted photograph of a portrait of Rev. Thomas M. Strong owned by Mrs. Strong.
    - History of the town of Flatbush (New York: Thomas R. Mercein Jr.), 1842 (Offsite-box RC-16, Envelope Strong. History of Flatbush, 1842)
  - Suydam, Ella (1897–1989) (EHHS librarian, 1919–195-)
    - [Letter from Mary A. Kingsbury recommending Suydam], 1922 May 17 (Offsite-box RC-5a, Folder Kingsbury, Mary A. Librarian)
      Letter written by Mary A. Kingsbury, first librarian of EHHS, to the Superintendent of the Board of Education, recommending awarding of a license to Miss Ella Suydam, who had been a substitute in the library for three years.
    - [Erasmus Hall scrapbooks], 1934, circa 1940 (Offsite-box RC-5b, Folder Erasmus Hall Library—Scrapbooks)
      Two 14 x 17" scrapbooks with text and illustrations, giving a history of the library of the Academy and the High School, compiled by librarian Ella Suydam:
  - Tennyson, Alfred, Lord (1809–1892)
    - Letter [facsimile], 1885 (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Autographs)
      English poet, laureate of England. Letter written in 1885 to the parents of Mrs. Lillian B. Croxson, 1911 Albermarle Rd. Presented to the Library Apr. 27, 1953. Note: The letter appears to be a reproduction of the original.
  - Theatre and Concert Programs
    - Scrapbook containing theatre and concert programs collected by Dr. J. Herbert Low, principal of Erasmus Hall High School, 1891–1893 (Offsite-box RC-16, Envelope N.Y.C. Theatre & Concert Programs)
  - Thompson, Benjamin F.
    - History of Long Island (2 vols.), 1843 (Offsite-box RC-17, Folder Wood, Silas | Thompson)
  - Tiles, Dutch
    - Dutch tile with picture of bird and decorative border [NOT PRESENT], [1700–1750] (Box [unknown])
      Dutch tile, about 4 ½ x 4 ½", with picture of bird and decorative border. n.d., but probably 18th century, first half.
      Recorded as being in Drawer 10.
    - Ten Dutch tiles depicting Biblical scenes, undated (Offsite-box RC-10c, Frame Wooden frame holding 10 tiles)
      Ten original Dutch tiles, each about 5 x 5", depicting Biblical scenes; framed.
      There is some question as to the provenance of these tiles. According to an article appearing in the school newspaper, The Dutchman, Apr. 3, 1936 (filed in folder marked "Fireplace," Records Case, Drawer 6), these tiles originally graced the fireplace of Erasmus Hall Academy, installed in 1787. However, there is good reason to believe that these tiles actually came from the fireplace in the old Zabriskie homestead which stood for almost 200 years on the northwest corner of Flatbush and Church Avenues, Brooklyn, until its demolition in 1877. The wooden frame is stamped in the lower right corner: "J.L.Z. 12.VI.1896." This is undoubtedly Reverend Jeremiah Lott Zabriskie (b. 1835) of Flatbush, who, according to Flatbush of To-Day (issued by All Souls Universalist Church, 1908, p. 141), owned the original tiles from the Zabriskie homestead, which were described as depicting events in Biblical history. He had apparently imbedded some of the tiles in the fireplace of his own home in 1886, where they remained in 1908; but these tiles framed in 1896 were undoubtedly also from the Zabriskie homestead.
      Further corroboration for this belief is found in the fact that many Zabriskie family heirlooms were donated to Erasmus Hall High School by Miss Louise Garvin Zabriskie. Among these are two wooden canisters made from beams in the old Zabriskie homestead, one of which bears the stamped inscription "J.L.Z. 1902." So it appears that Rev. Zabriskie was engaged in producing "souvenirs" of the old homestead for display, and embellishing them with his initials.
  - Trowel [NOT PRESENT]
    - Trowel used in laying cornerstone of Erasmus Hall High School [NOT PRESENT], [1905 January 17] (Box [unknown])
  - Truant Home
    - Report of Truant Home for the year ending Dec. 31, 1875, rendered by John L. Zabriskie, M.D., physician for the Home (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Academy Trustees' Correspondence)
      The report, in Zabriskie's hand and signed by him, is on the stationery of the "Kings County Penitentiary." Dr. Zabriskie notes that only one child died, and the death "took place after the child was removed to the Kings Co. Hospital."
  - Turner, Kate E. (EHHS assistant principal, 1898–1917)
    - [Program and clipping], 1917, 1937 (Offsite-box RC-2, Folder Kate E. Turner, asst. principal)
      • Program for farewell held for Miss Turner on Nov. 17, 1917 (2 copies).
      • Clipping about her retirement as principal of Bay Ridge High School, 1937.
    - Framed, autographed photo, undated (Offsite-box RC-9a, Folder Kate Turner framed, autographed photo)
  - Turner Medals
    - [Notebooks containing winners], 1921–1927 (Offsite-box RC-3a, Folder Notebooks listing winners of Turner Medals)
      • Notebook containing winners from January 1921 to January 1925. Also includes two pasted-in clippings listing winners of Holmes Medals.
      • Notebook containing winners from June 1925 to June 1927.
  - Twenty-One Seconds
    - "Twenty-One Seconds," published by the class of June 1942, 1939 (Offsite-box RC-4a, Folder EHHS—Misc. Publications)
      • Grade Two issue, May 1939 [2 copies]
  - U.S.S. Constitution
    - [Material from the hull of the U.S. Frigate Constitution], [1794 / 1927] (Offsite-box RC-10a, Folder Original material from the hull of the U.S. Frigate Constitution)
      "This material was taken from the original hull of the U.S. Frigate Constitution. Keel laid 1794. Rebuilding 1927."
      Two blocks of wood with the above inscribed on attached bronze plaques. The larger of the blocks also has a commemorative medal attached.
  - Van Brunt Family
    - Expenditures and receipts in the estate of Rutgert A. Van Brunt, as administered by John C. Vanderveer, 1818–1824 (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder Cowenhoven Family #1)
      Location: 2 pages at the rear of the 8 x 13" notebook filed with the Cowenhoven family papers.
      (For signature of Rutgert A. Van Brunt, see Martense Family.)
  - Vanderbilt, John
    - A receipt to Mr. John Vanderbilt..., 1830 (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Erasmus Hall Academy—Receipt for tuition of son of Judge John Vanderbilt, 1830)
  - Vanderveer, Cornelius
    - Sewel, W. A large dictionary English and Dutch (Amsterdam), 1708 (Offsite-box RC-17, Volume Spine: Woordenboek)
  - Vanderveer Family
    - [Receipt for farming], 1704 March 29 (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Vanderveer Family Documents, 1704, 1732)
      "Rec'd. this 29th March 1704 of Mr. John Cornelis Leu ye Sum of Three pounds for my Comishions farming ye ferry on Nassau Island & New York... (signed) Robt. Lurting V.D.Mr." Preserved between glass, 3 ½ x 8". Gift of W. R. Vanderveer, 3312 Glenwood Road.
    - [Doctor and funeral expenses of John Corneliusse Van Der Veer], [1732?] (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Vanderveer Family Documents, 1704, 1732)
      An account of money paid out by the children of John Corneliusse Van Der Veer, who died Nov. 23, 1732, for doctoring and funeral expenses. On the reverse, a signed receipt from Pieter Strycker for the church plot for the burial of Mr. Van Der Veer. Preserved between glass, 4 ½ x 8". Gift of W. R. Vanderveer, 3312 Glenwood Rd., Flatbush.
    - [Monies received for clothing and funeral of Adam, a slave], 1779 (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Vanderveer Family Document regarding funeral expenses of Adam, a slave, 1779)
      Account of amounts received from several Flatbush residents for "Cloathes and funeral" for Adam, who was the slave and personal attendant of Capt. Vanderveer. On reverse side, "A account of addam for the year 1779." This 6 ½ x 8 ½" document, preserved between glass, was a gift of W. R. Vanderveer, 3312 Glenwood Road.
    - Music book, [circa 1750–1800] (Offsite-box RC-16, Envelope Music books, late 18th c.)
      Music book, lacking title page and pp. 1–9, late 18th c., inscribed inside rear cover: "Jane Vanderveer, Ann Vanderveers Book."
  - Vanderveer Family—Windmill
    - "Expenditures of the Wind-Mill", 1803–1804 (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder Cowenhoven Family #1)
      This is the original expense account for the building of the famous windmill on the Vanderveer farm in Flatbush. According to Henry R. Stiles... History of Kings Co. (1884, v. 1, p. 227), "This is said to have been the first windmill erected on Long Island." It served as a refuge for the blacks in Flatbush during the 1863 draft riots, and burned in 1879.
      The two-page expense account appears in the center of the 8 x 13" notebook in the Cowenhoven family folder.
  - Van Kleek, (Rev.) Richard D. (Erasmus Hall Academy principal, 1843–1860)
    - The Christian Intelligencer, v. 14, no. 3, 1843 August 5 (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Principals of Erasmus Hall Academy (before 1896))
      Page 3 of this newspaper [published in New York by the Association of Members of the Protestant Reformed Dutch Church] contains an article announcing the appointment of Rev. Van Kleek as principal, and congratulating the Trustees for their fine choice.
      Gift of Natalie Wynkoop, 1574 50th St., May 23, ----.
    - [Letter of thanks], 1847 September 20 (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Principals of Erasmus Hall Academy (before 1896))
      Holograph letter, dated "Erasmus Hall Sept. 20, 1847" and signed "R. D. Van Kleek," thanking five of the Trustees for a gift. The letter sounds almost like a farewell, but Rev. Van Kleek continued to serve as principal until 1860.
  - Van Loon, Hendrik Willem (1882–1944)
    - [Two illustrated letters], 1924 May 22 & 26 (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Autographs)
      Dutch-born author and journalist. Two handwritten, hand-illustrated letters on a distinctive letterhead, dated May 22 and May 26, 1924, respectively. One is signed in full; the other is signed "Willem."
  - Vox Classica
    - "Vox Classica," published by the Classical Department of Erasmus Hall High School, 1935–1947 (Offsite-box RC-4a, Folder Latin publications (Vox Classica, Orbis Latinus))
      • Vol. 1, no. 1 (May 1935)
      • Vol. 1, no. 2 (Dec. 1935)
      • Vol. 1, no. 3 (Apr. 1936) [2 copies]
      • Vol. 1, no. 4 (May 1937)
      • Vol. 1, no. 5 (Apr. 1938) [2 copies]
      • Vol. 2, no. 1 (Apr. 1939) [4 copies]
      • Vol. 2, no. 2 (Apr. 1940)
      • Vol. 2, no. 3 (May 1941) [2 copies]
      • Vol. 7, no. 1 (May 1944)
      • Vol. A, no. 1 (Fall 1947) [2 copies]
  - Wells, Cornelius L. (Flatbush Reformed Dutch Church Minister)—Autographs
    - [Letter regarding Jared Hasbrouck], [1874] (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Academy Trustees' Correspondence)
      Letter, in pencil, regarding appointment of Jared Hasbrouck as principal of the Academy. Signed "C. L. Wells." n.d., but 1874 probably.
  - Westinghouse Awards
    - "Erasmus Hall High School Attains Highest Honors," Flatbush Magazine, 1962 February (Offsite-box RC-3a, Folder Awards)
      Clipping lists the record number of five EHHS winners in one year.
  - Wiggin, Kate Douglas (1856–1923) (Author of Rebecca of Sunnybrook Farm)
    - [Letters to J. Herbert Low], 1922 (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Autographs)
      Two autograph letters, signed, dated Oct. 28, 1922 and Nov. 1, 1922, signed "Kate D. Riggs (Kate Douglas Wiggin)," to Dr. J. Herbert Low, EHHS principal, regarding a talk delivered at Erasmus Hall by Miss Wiggin. Accompanied by carbon copies of Dr. Low's end of the correspondence.
  - Williams' New-York Annual Register
    - Williams, Edwin. The New-York annual register for the year of our Lord 1831 (Offsite-box RC-16, Envelope Williams' New-York Annual Register)
      Handsome woodcut of Erasmus Hall Academy opposite p. 159.
      Presented by Lewis E. Drummond.
  - Wilson, Peter, LL.D. (Erasmus Hall Academy principal, 1792–1805)
    - Wilson, Peter, LL.D. Compendium of Greek prosody, 1817 (Offsite-box RC-16, Envelope Wilson, Peter, LL.D. Compendium of Greek prosody)
      Inscribed on fly-leaf: "John A. Lott's Book, Flatbush, Long Island, Bought January 14, 1820 at Erasmus Hall, That is all."
  - Wood, Silas
    - Sketch of the first settlement of the several towns on Long Island... A new edition (Brooklyn: Spooner), 1828 (Offsite-box RC-17, Folder Wood, Silas | Thompson)
  - World War II
    - [Victory Liberty Loan flag], [1939–1945] (Offsite-box RC-3a, Folder WWII—including list of Erasmus boys who served)
      30 x 34" flag: Victory Liberty Loan Industrial Honor Emblem Awarded by U.S. Treasury Department.
  - World War II—Atomic Bomb Test
    - [Letter from P.F.C. R. C. Horlick to Miss F. R. Mastin], 1946 (Offsite-box RC-3a, Folder WWII—including list of Erasmus boys who served)
      Letter in special cacheted envelope, dated 1946, with following wording on envelope: "Atomic Bomb Test—Marshall Islands, Bikini Atoll—'Operation Crossroads'—U.S.S. Shangri-La." The letter is addressed to Miss F. R. Mastin, from P.F.C. R. C. Horlick. [Mastin = Florence Ripley Mastin (1887?–Feb. 23, 1968), poet and teacher at Erasmus Hall.]
  - Young Eagles
    - Young Eagles: An Anthology of Verse Written and Compiled by The Students of Erasmus Hall High School, Brooklyn, New York, 1953 (Offsite-box RC-11, Volume Young Eagles)
      Published by the General Organization. 92 p.
  - Young, Richard (Erasmus Hall patron, 1846–1935)
    - Letter to Dr. Gunnison thanking him for a copy of the Chronicles (1906) (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Correspondence Relating to the Chronicles of Erasmus Hall (1906))
    - Obituaries, memorial addresses, etc., [1935] (Offsite-box RC-2, Folder Richard Young (patron of Erasmus Hall))
      Richard Young, a successful businessman who made his home in Flatbush, was instrumental in the transfer of Erasmus Hall Academy to the City of Brooklyn, and in the erection of the new Erasmus Hall High School.
  - Zabriskie, John B., M.D. (1805–1848) (Flatbush physician)
    - Livingston, John H. The psalms and hymns, with the catechism, confession of faith, and liturgy of the Reformed Dutch Church in North America (New Brunswick: Deare & Terhune), 1814 (Offsite-box RC-16)
  - Zabriskie, John L., M.D.
    - Genealogy of the Lefferts family (Albany: Munsell), 1878 (Offsite-box RC-16)
    - Het Nieuwe Testament (Amsterdam), 1696 (Offsite-box RC-16)
      Inscribed inside rear cover, "Jeremeas Lott syn boek Anno 1788. With bookplate of Dr. John L. Zabriskie (1831–1895) of Flatbush.
  - Zabriskie Family
    Miss Louise Garvin Zabriskie apparently gave her collection of family papers to the EHHS Library about 1930, as it was soon before Mary A. Kingsbury's retirement in 1931. In a letter to Ella Suydam, July 8, 1934 (filed in Mary A. Kingsbury's folder, Records Case, Drawer 5), Miss Kingsbury wrote: "Did you find the papers that Miss Zabriskie left with us in that nice case? The last I knew of them, Mr. Mullen took the case and said he would take care of it. I do hope the papers are all right for my conscience has accused me many times of not keeping them in the library as she expected us to do. The trouble was that there didn't seem to be a place to spare even for that small case... ."
    The papers are preserved in the Erasmus Hall archives, though not as a unit.
    - Zabriskie family papers (box 1 of 2), undated (Offsite-box MS-28)
      • Papers relating to the Zabriskie family of Flatbush, including notebooks of Dr. John B. Zabriskie (1805–1848) and correspondence of Dr. John L. Zabriskie (1831–1895).
      • Also, much material relating to Miss Louise Garvin Zabriskie (1864–1963), who contributed much of the material in the Erasmus Hall Archives.
      • Also, original steel engraved printing plates for P. L. Schenck's The Zabriskie Homestead (1881).
    - Zabriskie family papers (box 2 of 2), undated (Offsite-box MS-29)